this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software ever thought about a master's
degree to advance your career as a
software developer the UC Irvine
16-month professionally oriented master
of software engineering program is made
for you taught by experts in the field
the program combines hands-on
experiences and fundamentals and latest
trends with professional development for
successful careers after graduation
hurry applications for fall 2019 or due
December 15th visit MSE ICS UCI GDU to
learn more and start your application
today this is Nate black for software
engineering radio my guest today is Jeff
our Soltani Jeff R is a lead developer
at rare a uk-based game studio that is
part of Microsoft Studios Jeff our leads
the deployment pipeline team which is
responsible for continuous delivery of
triple-a game titles Jeff our welcome to
software engineering radio hello thank
you for having me
it's great to have you here Jeff er I'm
just going to mention for our listeners
that our overall topic today is
continuous delivery in games but
continuous delivery is something that
we've covered in the past on several
shows and a few resources that our
listeners might check out our episode
221 Jess humble on continuous delivery
and recently episode 340 Laster on
Jenkins - but our topic today is going
to be specifically continuous delivery
in games which provides a unique set of
challenges and your talk is your talk at
pipeline conference 2018
implementing continuous delivery for
Triple A games was something that
motivated our discussion today and
that's also something that listeners can
check out on YouTube so Jeff art briefly
before we get started could you please
describe your role at rare show so I've
been working at ran for over 10 years
now and as you mentioned I lead
deployment pipeline team here at red and
this is a team that didn't exist
previously on previous games for the
current game that we developing which is
called sea of thieves which we started
about four years ago we knew that we
need to adopt consciously which we can
I'm sure we going to go through them in
this episode and in order to achieve
that we we sat down and discuss and we
said we really need a team focused on
helping us to adopt conscience delivery
so that's how this team was formed and I
started leading this team because
previously we had the tools team we had
the build team we had a release team and
this is really a team that combines all
of these skills in in one bigger team we
are we are about 9 10 developers in our
team for the for the scale of the game
that we are working on and I can go
through the different responsibilities
that we have if you interested okay I
think that that's something we can talk
about a little bit later in the
implementation section let's first get
to some basic definition so we can have
a common understanding about what we're
talking about
absolutely first what is continuous
delivery so continuous delivery is the
set of practices that then allows us to
release the game to play as any time we
want anytime there is a good reason to
do so and maybe it's worth mentioning at
this point like how the games are
developed traditionally because the
games are not generally developed with
continuous delivery in mind but for us
here even at rare this is the first time
we are adopting continuous delivery it's
been a long journey
previously and this is the same with a
lot of other Triple A games that the
project takes about usually three years
and it's based on mostly based on a
waterfall methodologies where you have a
big planning upfront you do some we call
a pre-production which you try to
identify the game the story behind the
game and then once these are all proven
and also some technical challenges you
try to prove them all up front then once
you got your funding then you go into
the production or basically your
development where you develop the game
and towards the end of it usually the
last three months or so is bug-fixing
phase where we try to work together work
really long hours crunch to make sure
all the bugs are fixed so we can release
at a certain date and once the game is
released we might do a couple of updates
afterwards and that team then is
finished and they go and move on to the
next game so that's the traditional
model for for this game because we
wanted to develop this game as a service
which means we wanted to release
frequently and keep updating the game
and adopting the game based on the
feedback we receive from our players and
our community that was one of the main
reasons that we decided then to apply
continuous delivery practices and it
talked okay so normally what you do is a
big waterfall process where first you
did some validation up front and I'm I'm
curious to find out more about what that
validation is that you do before you get
the funding but before we go to that I
want to get a little bit more into
continuous delivery and like what what
it actually is or how its how how is it
different or similar to continuous
integration or continuous deployment you
talked about it as being able to release
anytime you want
get to the user could you talk about
that a little bit more show so how is it
related to continuous integration for
example sure so continuous integration
is another set of practices that is a
prerequisite for continued delivery
when you'd apply when you practice
continuous integration it means
everybody is working on the same branch
which is usually called trunk so all the
developers everybody work in the same
branch and they trying to commit to that
trunk at least daily sometimes is
encouraged to do it more frequently so
you are generally trying to work in
small batches or you don't you don't and
end up working on it on a code for like
a week and then checking at the end you
try to break it down into smaller
incremental steps and then try to check
in those changes as regularly as
possible and we then what we do is are
we then run by this sort of validation
that needs to be really fast on on these
changes to get fast feedback so what you
also get as part of practicing connie's
integration is fast feedback that your
change hasn't broken anything
which ultimately leads to better quality
because the sooner you find that problem
is the sooner you can fix them therefore
the overall quality increases so once
you have that in place then that allows
you to once you've added into your game
then it allows you to automate your
deployment which then in turn allows you
to then release that if you want the
difference between continuous delivery
and continuous deployment is with
conscious deployment any changes is
potentially is pushed to players or to
user so you check in a change a set of
tests automated tests run and the end is
introduced to to your users that works
great for a lot of web products when
updating new version is pretty much
seamless for your clients or customers
whereas with games similar to mobile
applications is every time you release
you have to go through a certification
process that the platform holder like
Microsoft in our case have and as part
of going through that process that it
takes some time but players then have to
download a new version so imagine every
time you try to play the game is prompt
you there are you need to update that
could be quite frustrating if you what's
happening multiple times a day so that's
and that's one of the challenges here
too because we want to
as frequently as possible but at the
same time we need to make sure that the
experience for a play is this seal is
acceptable so continuous integration is
a set of practices that results in small
incremental changes being checked into
the same branch so that you have
something that is always releasable with
every check in and then continuous
delivery will result in some artifact
that you can potentially push to
customers but not necessarily and yes
deployment would be if you were pushing
those artifacts to customers all the
time so it sounds like you're you're
going to continuous delivery so you have
that releasable artifact but you're not
necessarily deploying it all the time
because you're that's exactly correct
yes okay because you're doing extra
validation but then also you don't want
to harass users with every single change
list resulting in an update and another
difference big difference between games
and other like special equip products is
what are you talking about the game
package the the artifact that is
generated at the end of the pipeline it
could be 50 gigabyte or even hundred
abite so the size is quite large
compared to other other software so you
don't want kind of your play so you have
to keep downloading multiple gigabyte
every every day otherwise you are fairly
soon going to lose a lot of them
understood yeah so there's a lot of
bandwidth it would potentially be needed
there yeah of course yeah and that's
good one of the things that we
constantly work on to make sure what we
are releasing what we are giving to our
players is absolutely the minimum that
they need this change which the the
platform such as Xbox provides a great
tooling for us because it does some
differential checking and only gives to
the team amounts of bits that has
actually changed since last night
they've downloaded it so they don't have
to redownload the the parts that they
already have it hasn't changed
that's interesting I'd like to get into
more details about the tooling show them
after first I before I move on to the
next section
I just wanted to
capture something you said earlier
because I wanted to ask about what the
values are or what the overall goal is
that you have for continuous delivery
and what I got out of your description
so far is that you get faster feedback
because you're able to deploy faster and
that this results in higher quality
that's crazy that it or is there
something I missed no that that's quite
right but there are other benefits as
well that that's one of the benefits I
can go through the rest as well so the
other benefits are we look traditionally
we are releasing a huge amount of
content to players at the end of that
two years three years time that I
mentioned whereas what we trying to do
in this case because this is a game as a
service we need to be able to
sustainably delivering new features over
a long period of time and that again we
can do this by adopting continued
delivery and making sure we have
candidates almost daily maybe even
multiple times a day
the other thing it also helps us is
because as I mentioned every looking
traditionally every time we were going
we were releasing the game everybody
were crunching and working longer hours
the weekends and in this model where you
are basically sustainably delivering new
features and releasing all the time if
you are not adopting conscious delivery
you end up pretty much crunching all the
time and you have instead of conscious
delivery you have continues crunch which
is not really sustainable for for
developers for ourselves so we wanted to
definitely minimize the amount of crunch
and overtime that our developers have to
do and therefore have happier developers
as a result of that and the lighting the
another main benefit is because
traditionally for games
there aren't many automated tests being
written we are heavily relying on an
army of manual testers to test the game
but then the problem with that is if you
are releasing all the time that means we
need to hire them for all the time well
traditionally you hire them for the last
six months of the project whereas in
this model you have to basically hard
all the time and what's even worse is
the moment that you don't have them you
don't have any confidence to make any
more changes so it's not really all of
that money is not really an investment
unlike the automation because like once
you spend the time and wrote those
automations that is they're always gonna
be there and you can always run them
whereas in this case you you pay for
having a large manual testing and as
soon as you don't pay for that then you
don't basically have nothing if
traditionally you have this army of
manual testers and now you're starting
to rely more on automated test does this
mean that you have a small number of
testers that is always part of the team
or how does the team composition change
yes that's a great question
yes that's definitely true that's
definitely like the like I said
previously we had probably about 100
over hundred testers I would say
probably on the previous projects
whereas now we had probably less than
even ten testers I would say and quite a
few of them were embedded in each
because we have like multiple smaller
teams the work on different features of
the game and they were kind of embedded
there providing early feedback for
developers and they are they're mainly
not to do what the automated tests do
for us but they were there to do what
humans are are capable of doing they are
there to give us feedback about the game
itself whether it's fun or do some
exploratory testing obviously if they
find problems that the game crashes or
is unstable they will lock bugs and then
we go and fix them but that's not really
their job their job is there to do the
things that are human made of for okay
so they're able to provide more value
because instead of just doing things
that the automated test could do they're
doing things that only humans can do
which exactly maybe some more quality
qualitative or or subjective and
computers don't really have ability to
do those things definitely yes that's
correct
okay moving on to the next part of the
discussion we started talking about this
a little bit already but I want
to give our listeners a better idea
about Triple A games like what they are
and in particular I think most everyone
knows what video games are but what is
it that defines a Triple A game
so Triple A games are certain
characteristics they are mainly written
in C++ there are generally monolithic
applications and this is a big team
usually between 300 to 500 people
involved in making these games so there
are quite a large scale and they take a
long time said mainly look it could be
from 2 years up to like three or four
years to work on the game to release so
it takes a long time as well and there
are not many automated tests written
they mainly rely on manual testers the
other big difference is that they are
treated as mainly lockbox products so
you have this one big release with a lot
of celebration and then a couple of
releases afterwards but other
characteristics for maybe for people who
play the game is these they usually have
extremely high quality graphics and
these games really push the capabilities
of hardware they run on to the limits
and one of the challenges always to try
to achieve more from the hardware that
you have and the amount of content there
is is enormous so you have a big content
team which is part of that 300 to 500
people who dedicate it to develop the
environment the textures the models the
animations and special audio as well so
you have different disciplines involved
in making the game so it's not just
software developers you have artists you
have designers and you have some
producers as well and that's pretty much
pretty much it and quite a lot of them
run on consoles but the same time a lot
of them run on PCs do people usually
work on a single game over an extended
period of time or two developers hop
from one project to another project I
think it depends on the other company
but for us we are mainly what we mainly
work on one game
some would say some of the other maybe
other companies who work on maybe on the
smaller games they can work on multiple
games at the same time but what kind of
these big triple-a titles requires so
much effort that realistically with when
you do make 300 to 500 people involved
for one project managing like multiple
projects at st. Anne would be quite
challenging so I think is pretty much
like developers working on the same
project for number of years I see what
about in terms of specialization I
thought that developers might hop from
one project to another if say they were
really good at a particular aspect of
graphics optimization or something like
that or perhaps network programming yes
I mean we have people who are very
specialized I mean what we tend to do
generally is to promote people to work
on different things as opposed to just
work on graphics as you mentioned
because in terms of the organization and
the performance of an organization when
you have generalist and the people who
are capable of working on different
areas when there is a need it's easier
to mobilize people and move them to work
on those other areas that you need as
opposed to saying us all are that's a
graphics program are busy so we can't
afford to move them but there are
certain people who really enjoy working
going really really deep and being
extremely specialized in certain areas
but generally as I said we promote
developers here to to work on as many
areas as they can and for instance when
I started my career and rare I was doing
graphics programming on Viva Pinata 2
and Banjo Kazooie and then I moved into
tools development and eventually the
deployment pipeline team so people quite
often they're people especially in our
company move around a lot I see that's
interesting yes I mean it helps because
like people just learn different skill
sets and therefore become a better
developers at the end of the day yeah
I'm surprised that for some reason I'd
imagined that people became more
specialized but I think it's interesting
that you promote people being
generalists and it I think I understood
why because it makes them more flexible
and hopping from one part of the
1 an area of the project to another so
you're more lean in a sense one thing
you mentioned about games as
applications is that they're monolithic
what what does that mean so that means
like they're not very modular
unfortunately what you compile at the
end is just one big executable so like
there are other architecture like
service-oriented architecture which and
micro services for instance where you
have a lot of smaller applications that
they all interact with each other
whereas the games that's unfortunately
not the case one of the main reason is
the for performance reasons just having
everything as one binary and it's
critical speed things up significantly
but at the same time he has his own
downsize one of the bigger downsides is
the how long it takes to compile the
game and Link the game that's one of the
one of the big problems there it is
quite common that he might take
sometimes half an hour to an hour to
compile the whole game which is very
long time so then it impacts the
iteration time for developers because
Reggie you make a change and then you
what you would like to view that change
and you have to wait for an hour to see
and then you notice there's another
problem so another hour so you soon
realize that you can only do a couple of
attempts in a day to test your change
really which isn't very sustainable so
again as part of our team deployment
pipeline team we spend a lot of time
trying to optimize the build time so we
can compile as quickly as possible so
for us it takes about ten minutes just
to give you an example
comparison to other game titles are
their incremental approaches to
compiling that you do during development
time or as there are reasons that you
found it that that's not a viable
approach no definitely so we did a lot
of work to make sure we can reliably
build the game incremental that's
definitely one thing that we did that
had its own challenges because what we
what we do is we have a build form of
150 physical built machines and they all
have two CPUs
which is like with 20 courses dogs are
quite powerful pcs and what we found is
the status of these machines between
each runs is not very predictable
because they might compile the game and
the certain change list number at
certain point in time and then there
will not compile anything for a while
and then a couple of hours and then the
compiler and you see these times are not
very consistent depending on when was
the last time that the build happened on
a PC so that is one of the challenges to
make sure we can keep these times
consistent the other thing we do is we
use distributed build systems so even
though these machines have like 40 cores
we still use systems that allows us to
use other people's idle cores so when
let's say they are not using their pcs
they can contribute to the bill form and
we can use that to compile the code
that's another another option but also
having really fast hard disks it helps a
lot because when you build your writing
and reading a lot of fun is the disk so
like we are using for engines nvme
drives and all our build forms and our
developers PC because that significantly
improves the time to compile the game
and other other things are like looking
at the code generally identifying for
instance when when you find particular
font that is slow to compound we try to
simplify that file for instance because
these are all C++ so they are the
simplest code might be including a lot
of other header files so but going
through and making sure we are not
including everything and or some of the
base classes that we don't necessarily
need and removing them helps a lot so
these are the the challenges there but I
think an area of improvement potentially
especially with these large-scale C++
code is to use incremental build but at
a distributed level so let's assume that
you are making a change you're probably
touching about maybe less than 5% of the
code
bass and if you could use the other 95%
from other people when they compared the
game then your compiler would reduce
significantly obviously we don't have
that technology available for us like we
don't have it I think there are some
tools available in the market that helps
but we haven't tried them because if you
think about it like as opposed to
everybody has to compile that
ninety-five percent it don't change it's
a lot of wasted kind of CPU and power
that you can avoid it sounds like you
were describing that arranging your code
in a certain way can actually impact a
build time that's great I didn't
understand how could you explain that a
little bit more sure so let's say let's
talk about the header files for instance
let's say we are including some header
files that we don't need because the C++
the way is compound
he runs a preprocessor that looks at all
these header files and try to add them
to your basic module when you try to
compile them and the more of those you
have the longer obviously takes to
compile them and process them so by
really removing a lot of these
unnecessary header files it helps a lot
and also there are techniques in C++
like forward declaring a lot of types it
helps as well because there's a need to
include the content of those header
files in your in your compilation module
there to compile that's one of the one
of the big things also there are other
concepts such as unity builds in C++
which is it's a technique that is kind
of debatable sometimes it helps
we don't necessarily use that that
allows basically creating bigger C++
files by including other sequence files
inside them we don't necessarily use
that much but that's another technique
to help speed up C++ code well for us
mainly the things that helps us is
removing the code we don't really need
to include having fast disks and a lot
of CPU and using distributed build
systems so we can utilize other people
basically the ideal Coors takes us to a
good position okay maybe we can revisit
this and the implementation section I
want to stay high level for a little bit
longer and try to understand taking sea
of thieves as an example what kind of
game is it in terms of networking
multiplayer graphics or gameplay or any
other aspects of the game you think
describe it
sure so sea of thieves is a it's a
multiplayer cooperative at the venture
game where there is no predefined story
for the game unlike some other games
that have a strong narrative story the
story is imagined based on the
interaction of players with each other
and their environment and you have to
play this online so you can't play on
your own offline you have to be online
when you play the game so there's our
kind of architecture we have a client
that people download on their console
err on their PC to run you have a server
that multiple clients connect to and we
have a set of services and those
services are not written in C++ they are
written in C sharp and are using
microservices architecture that provide
a lot of capability for the game and
that's kind of the structure in terms of
the graphics it's very kind of realistic
graphics like the water if you look at
the water
it is very realistic and it's very
beautiful at the same time so it's a lot
of effort put in to make the the graphic
looks great okay so I understood there's
a client and that's the monolithic
application that's written in C++ and
it's distributed to the users to their
xbox is it also on PC or is it just as
correct yes so they can people can play
it on PC and Xbox okay
and server is the same server is the
same monolithic C++ code the server is
the same monolithic C++ code that is run
on a client no no no survey runs in the
cloud so that runs on on Azure and the
crime is connected to that okay but this
server you said is also written in C++
and is their shared code between the
client and the server or the server is
its own no no so the code there's a
proportion of the code that is shared
between both client and server because
at the end of the day they need to
understand what how they're
communicating with each other but when
we are compiling we have to compile the
client separately to the server because
the server for instance doesn't have a
lot of the code that the client has and
the package for the server that we
create that we upload to the cloud is
significantly smaller than the client
because register client needs to have
all their or the assets who that I mean
what I mentioned was the size of the
game can be fifty two hundred gigabyte
and what you find is probably a tiny
proportion of that is just executable
the rest of it is just the art and audio
assets like the textures the animation
the sound effects the visual effects and
all of those constitute most of that
data whereas a server doesn't need all
of those assets because like you're not
trying to render anything on a server
side it's mainly there to compute things
and and be the authority to tell the
Congress what needs to happen there so
we need to basically to make two
separate packages one for the client and
one for the server ok so there is some
shared code but it's compiled it's
compiled separately for a client and
server because on server you're
stripping out or just not including the
graphical assets etc that's correct that
is correct yes and maybe we need to get
a little bit into the game design or
perhaps the
the way that the game is structured
because it sounds like that there's some
some shared state or some simulation
that's happening that's in common
between the client and the server yes
not necessarily the part that's rendered
but you said the authoritative States so
what I'm imagining from that is that
when I move my character in the game
that my the commands that move my
character or perhaps the location of my
character has to be reflected on the
server so that everyone who's
participating in the game can get that
data and that because you want things to
be consistent you're doing the same
simulation on the client and the server
is that correct yes you're absolutely
right yes and when I say authoritative I
mean that less as you said like crying
let's say calculus is position because
like given is our game and let's say the
game has a ship and the players are on
the ship and the ship is moving based on
a certain speed and so crankin
calculates where it's heading in the
direction and the position in the future
and the server does the same thing and
but if the client and server end up
disagreeing on where the position should
be the server corrects the client and
that's kind of one of the ways for us to
kind of prevent cheating because like
let's say some people as opposed to
trying to run or let's say they can
somehow they could increase the speed
that they they can say that would be
corrected back because of the server
code there because that's what he tells
the crying to do that makes sense yes
but as you said it is running a lot of
simulation on the server okay so so far
we talked about the the model with a
client the dedicated server which is in
a sense a subset of that client but we
didn't talk about the services that the
part that's written in c-sharp
what do those services do so services
are there to complement the client and
server and they are there to communicate
extra information both to server and the
client for example let's say that your
find information storing what you like
let's say you are accumulating gold in
the game so that information needs to be
stored somewhere and then communicated
back all of that is done through
services or the other thing we use it is
for configuration so if we want to let's
say change some configuration of the
game we do that via the services so then
when it's updated then they both the
client and server can get that
information another thing that we use
them for is the feature toggles which is
one of the enabler for us to use trunk
based development and manage to stay the
same so it sounds like the dedicated
server is handling things related to the
running state of the game like if I'm in
the game and I'm playing it my players
moving around all the real-time stuff
and the services are doing things that
maybe don't have that same real-time
quality instead of rough yeah I think
that's especially like the server
doesn't remember any kind of states or
anything about the game so when you
start a new server it starts from fresh
it doesn't remember what you were doing
before whereas the services are kind of
responsible for getting all of that
information and pass it to both client
and server and I suppose that in your
talk and in what we've described so far
about the continuous delivery related to
games the special part is the client and
dedicated server part that's written in
C++ because these server services that
are deployed on Azure would probably be
not too different from ordinary web
services that we talk about regularly on
this program absolutely yes you're
actually right that's correct the the
main challenge is the client and the
server
especially the client sorry cuz still
with the server as you mentioned the
server is in in the cloud so we can
deploy server how many times you want
and that wouldn't have necessarily
noticeable impact for players whereas
the client is the main
in main thing that players are
interacting with and that's the main
main challenge there because every time
you update it would be a friction
potentially with players okay one thing
that you mentioned in your talk was that
only 5% to 10% of the project consists
of code correct yes what what makes up
the other 90 to 95%
we called them assets which are art and
audio assets mainly in the video so
let's say like because the game
especially triple ax game with a high
level of quality the graphics and the
audio so they need high resolution
textures they need animation models they
whole environment the whole world the
audio the sound effects all of that and
the videos the cutscenes that you see in
the game they all consume majority of
the of that 90 to 95 percent but I think
our executable for us is probably 150
megabyte which is not small but
relatively speaking when the whole
package is like between 30 to 50
gigabyte 150 meg is very very small
percentage of that hmm but obviously
that's millions lines of code so sillies
quite big now when you're creating these
builds that take potentially hours to
complete or if you're able to do your
job well get it down to minutes and with
your parallelized build process is the
time it's most of the time and to build
going to you just the C++ compiler or is
there other processing that's happening
on these assets as part of your build
pipeline this is both compiling is is a
big chunk but more time is spent on as
you said processing those assets because
they need to be converted to format
specifically for a platform that you are
releasing on let's say our artists work
on on textures and say they they can
work in in any kind of normal like kind
of software or the models are they
developed let's say they develop it in
3d studio max or Maya but that model we
cannot load that direct as it is on on
Xbox because it's not very efficient I
mean one of the main reason is
efficiency for us because what we
ideally what we want to do we want to
load the asset as it is into memory and
make sure everything is aligned and is
compacted as much as possible so we
don't consume a lot of memory because
one of the challenges with especially
with triple a game because of a lot of
high resolution assets is amount of
memory that is required to load so
making sure that we kind of strip out
any pieces of information that is not
relevant for the game that allows us
then to to load them better and achieve
a better performance because that means
we can get into the game faster because
we have managed to load all the required
assets faster so that that is quite
important but it that part can take a
very long time to go through each asset
strip out the unneeded information and
make sure they are compacted and aligned
so therefore they unloaded faster ok
so at one end of the pipeline you have
the artists that are creating the rough
raw files or whatever the working format
is for those files and there's a process
where they're converted down into the
thing that the computer or the Xbox is
natively good at rendering exactly yes
and I've I've heard this part of the
process described as a pipeline just on
its own the asset pipeline yes
so I'm it makes me a little confused
because on one hand we're talking about
deployment pipeline then we had the
asset pipeline and it sounds like your
team is kind of combining through tools
and through processes combining these
into one continuous delivery pipeline is
that how you think of it or how do you
define and use the word pipeline or is
it context dependent no that's that's an
excellent observation that's absolutely
right because you said like you could
have an asset pipeline you could also
have the code pipeline because like
you're compiling the code
and generating an output at the end of
it but the deployment pipeline is
basically combination of all of these
different pipelines that you have
because at end of the day each of these
pipelines result in this one package
that we create for our players to to be
able to release that and having one kind
of looking at all of this as one
pipeline and even one team looking after
this means that when we are optimising
we are optimizing for the global end to
end time because it's not great if we
have a super fast let's say compile time
but our asset pipeline is very very slow
because I didn't have a day that's our
bottleneck and if the code is really
fast you can part but then it takes like
a day to convert all the assets we
haven't really achieved much because
still the rate that we can release would
be by how long it takes for us to
convert the assets so by treating both
of them as as just one pipeline because
we also have to think about audio assets
audio assets are very similar to the art
asset that we mentioned there are in the
raw format that needs to be converted
into the format that can be played on an
Xbox so by treating all of them as kind
of one pipeline looking after them helps
massively I'm glad that you described it
that way because I was planning to ask
what is the thing you're trying to
optimize its the maybe the cycle time
which we call a cycle time is the time
it takes to go through this pipeline
which is basically from the time that
somebody has wants to make a change
until we can release that change to
players that's kind of the time that we
trying to optimize got it okay I think
now is a good time to jump into the
implementation so how you went from not
having a pipeline team to having your
team and the continuous delivery
pipeline we've we've been talking about
at the pipeline conference in your
presentation you described how you
implemented continuous delivery for CF
thieves
and you said that this was a first
the company so I'm curious why hadn't
this been done before a couple of
reasons I think especially with the I
mean this is a wrong assumption but a
lot of people make unfortunately the
wrong assumption or we were making the
same wrong assumption which is because
you are releasing once every three four
years people might assume that there is
no value in doing continuous delivery
because they might say that I we are
working on this codebase it doesn't
really matter if it doesn't compile or
the game crashes or features are not
integrated we but they focus on
developing these features as quickly as
possible and then spend the last part of
the project trying to kind of glue all
of these things together make sure the
performance is acceptable
make sure the memory is under the budget
this the reliability of the game is high
so it doesn't crash it's stable and bugs
are fixed and then and they rarely have
to maintain that codebase after they
released so a lot of practices that we
we talk about in continuous delivery
like the benefits of main
maintainability people don't see that
even though they're working on the code
base for like three to four years and
they have to deal with maintainability
and slowness if you're not really
tackling technical debts they just
assume that because at the end of it the
project they kind of they throw away the
code and start again
they you can afford to that which is a
completely wrong assumption to make but
the other reason is this is it's hard
it isn't easy and like we started this
about four years ago and we are going
through we have made huge progress but
still there are plenty of things that we
can improve so it's not like a simple
thing to change and also requires a lot
of cultural change because our
developers for instance when we started
they were not used to writing tests and
a lot of people still assume that it's
not developers role to write tests which
is not quite right so having to convince
the developers that actually they need
to write tests and why they need to
write tests was quite important at least
it could be quite challenging so I think
these are probably the reasons they're
not like we certainly adopted in the
past
and also not many other companies
unfortunately but as we have seen with
the benefits even though at the moment
we already sink once a week we can do it
more frequent as well if you want but I
think what we found is releasing once a
week is a good rhythm for us but even if
we were releasing once every month but
having these candidates it just gives us
confidence that when we get to that
point we have many candidates
potentially that we can choose to
release it's basically looking at the
different feature sets in each of these
candidates and pick the best one
ready the traditional model you only
have one candidate and that's the one
that you made the day before which adds
a lot to the risk
I see so it was hard to implement
because you hadn't done it before it
costs a lot in resources it sound like
you have a team of 10 people or so that
are dedicated to this and on top of this
you had to change the culture getting
developers to be comfortable writing
tests to understand that that's part of
their role if they want to create a high
quality product
absolutely yes but also developers like
you need to change it mindset for the
developers because again traditionally
they kind of used to the fact that they
go and work on a on a piece of code on a
feature for a week couple of weeks and
then they check in at the end so they
they basically summer this massive
change and again changing that mindset
to say no you need to break this down
into small increments that's is a skill
itself regardless of whether you do
continue integration because it's
delivery or anything but getting
developers to change how they approach
solving problems but not trying to solve
the problem at the end but try to solve
it in incremental steps was another big
challenge for us and how has the team
adapted to that quite well I would like
I think if we were deciding to go back
to the old model a lot of people would
not be happy I think cuz once you work
this way and you can see that you can
make a change be able to give it to the
players within a day or two at most
that's a it's very rewarding because
otherwise like you're working on a
feature and you probably not gonna give
it to players for a year
so you're really not gonna see the
impact on your change whereas in this
case you are working and then you you're
like now and then you give it two days
later to the players and they can see
how they reacted because you can see the
community that
if you release a new feature what they
had they responded there also that fast
feedback that developers get is really
really rewarding I think digital ocean
is the easiest cloud platform to deploy
manage and scale applications of any
size we're moving infrastructure
friction and providing predictability so
developers and their teams can deploy
faster and focus on building software
that customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/sc radio I see so you said earlier that
it was more sustainable way of working
because it's not a continuous crunch
absolutely yes that's another doesn't
know the important thing could stay like
some people might crunch but I think
that's the nature of games because like
everybody wants people want to produce
the best possible version of the thing
that they working on because it's kind
of they they have the extremely proud of
what they are working so isn't its
natural that people want to kind of cram
as much as possible up to the last
minute but it's certainly like first of
all this is voluntarily like some people
do and it's not like consistent like you
might working on one specific feature
you really want to keep this out so you
might kind of do a couple of over times
but then you go back and so in the
deployment pipeline is there a
centerpiece of the architecture like
something like Jenkins that's your build
server that's that controls everything
yeah yeah we use Team CT with you you
like or the CI server yes okay yeah we
can talk we hope you can talk about
those yeah let's talk about that a
little bit like is it how does it work
you you have a bunch of scripts that you
configure to run in a certain order or
what what does it look like at a
practical level yes so as I mentioned we
use teamcity as our CI server
and for a source control we are using
perforce which is a centralized source
control system and we have a bunch of
scripts and tools that we have written
that we execute on teamcity
and they are responsible for compiling
the game converting the assets we have
written a testing framework ourselves
which we run on teamcity as well and
report the test but at the same time we
wrote a lot of tools to be able to
collect the relevant information when we
run tests to be able to report them to
developers so Bernie when it has fails
is easy for them to identify what caused
the failure and in terms of the the size
of our infrastructure that we use we
have about 150 physical pcs the way that
we use and there are quite powerful pcs
the two CPUs with a lot of memory and
very fast network and this and a lot of
disk storage in terms of the amount of
data that we generate I think we
generate about 10 terabyte of data every
day so it's quite a lot and in terms of
the test number of tests that we have
written we have about 60,000 tests and I
think we run about 4 or 5 million tests
per day and you know our test about 90%
of them are unit tests and the rest are
more tests of focus on larger area of
the code or some integration tests some
performance tears or some memory tests
that we have does that answer your
question
yes so so teamcity is the centerpiece
that's where the control is done of the
overall process
sounds like does that also handle
orchestration of those hundred and fifty
machines or is that a separate piece
that's correct
that happens through teamcity but give
it like we have a form of 100 to 50
machines we also use some monitoring
systems to monitor the health of these
pcs because at any given time there
could be a couple of them to have issues
either the dimmer on disk space or
there might be slow for whatever reason
if they have a heart fault there might
be a flying so we are using Splunk
to monitor the infrastructure as well
and is the entire infrastructure
windows-based yes it is I mean as you
mentioned earlier as well like we are
part of Microsoft I mean the main reason
that we use Windows is because we are
releasing all windows but in terms of
the tools that we use we use the tools
that make sense like for instance we use
perforce because most of the game
companies use after you centralize
source control system unfortunately we
can't really use gate first because of
the scale and the other problem is the
size of the data and the amount of code
that you have to think in a sense but
also with the with the art asset that we
talked about they are stored mainly as
binary format which means that you can't
really marriage these files so it's
quite important that when you're editing
this you lock these farms so other
people would not accidentally change
them because otherwise when you finish
already you have to overwrite their
change or you will lose your change
instead it sounded like if your binary
files that come from your art assets get
out of sync with the code that that can
cause real problems and that's part of
the reason that you were using trunk
based development yes that's that's
quite right because some I've heard that
some other maybe other games what they
do is they have probably even like a
separate event source control system or
or even some different branch for the
content the assets but as you said it's
a challenge to make sure the game when
the game changes they can still read
those formats and they can go out of
sync and what we found is generally
simpler to keep both the content and the
code in the same branch although I have
to say what we what we do is the source
assets the role formats are we talking
about they are not in the same place
just like they are quite mass
as well and we don't want everybody to
necessarily sink them so they are kind
of separated but the output of those
assets that are converted to the format
they can be used in the game or in the
next to the code that we have which is
the game it actually reminds me a lot of
developing against a large database
where your code is heavily dependent on
the database schema and these schema
changes always have to go out before
your code changes go out so that's part
of the incremental process first you
change the schema then you change the
code and there have to be known
boundaries for Windows changes happen
yes yeah absolutely I'm in the past like
we use versioning as well so your cue
version your asset so and then but you
have to make sure you are backward
compatible as well so when you make
change against you load these different
version of assets and update them but so
generally we found that it's simpler if
we keep everything in one branch and
don't have a make sure when you sync the
head everything should work as is
expected okay so you call this trunk
based development and in this case the
trunk must be what you call the main
branch in perforce and gate it would be
called master or it might be called
trunk in SVN but you are contrasting
this with feature branch based
development can you talk a little bit
more about that the differences
absolutely yes
so the the main difference is like
everybody walk in the same branch which
is this in main or trunk whereas with
the feature branches you can have a
feature team they go away work on a
separate branch and once they they
finish developing their feature then
they integrate they change back into the
main there were there are a couple of
problems with this approach one of the
the first problem is if let's as I
mentioned the assets are binary format
so if you are working on certain assets
in your feature branch and somebody
happens to make a change to the same
assets in the main branch when you get
to integrate your changes back to me you
have to overwrite one or the other so
you might lose that and what we know is
that the longer it takes
and the bigger the changes the more
painful it is to marriage that back and
this is one of the ideas behind
continues integration by doing
integration back into the main branch
frequently daily or even more frequently
than daily you are reducing that painful
merge conflict to to the minimum
possible pain the other problem is when
you are working on a separate branch
your feedback loop loop is extremely
long because until you merge your change
back and integrate your feature into the
main game you know you're not going to
get any feedback about your change so by
working on the same on on main trunk you
can check in and a couple of hours later
you can see that your change how is
interacting with everybody else has
changed so you get extremely fast
feedback compared to the feature
branches and also on top of that if you
have multiple feature branches and you
fix the critical issue in let's say
trunk then now you have to integrate the
same changed multiple branches and
depending on how out-of-date they are it
could be quite difficult thing to do we
used to have feature branches it wasn't
fun at all too many examples come to
mind of particularly painful merge
experience from a feature branch sure
like one of the games that we worked
about like six seven years ago which was
a sports game so we had multiple
different sports and each one was
developing their own branches you kind
of made sense at that point in terms of
logically because somebody working on a
game of tennis they were working on
their own branch and then I don't know
somebody is working on a game of bowling
they work on a different branch and what
we were doing at that point was we were
intending to integrate changes back to
main at the beginning of the week to
make a bill so then we can get our
feedback but often what we found was we
started this process on Monday and
usually took on till Wednesday or
Thursday until all of these changes were
integrated and compiling successfully so
it was a it was very painful and a lot
of a lot time-consuming I remember
spending a lot of late nights trying to
merge these changes back with the help
of the developers
working on these features so and so
imagine that you work on an honor
feature you don't get any feedback that
week and of the following week is when
you get feedback about your change so
the feedback loop is a lot longer
whereas right now as a match and
developers work on a feature they take
it in and potentially we can really set
within a day so they can see the impact
of your change so it's the difference
between an hour and potentially a week
possibly yes sometimes it could be even
longer depending on how often you choose
to integrate maybe we're doing it weekly
but it's not uncommon for somebody not
to integrate anything and wait until the
feature is fully complete although it's
not really complete because you don't
know if it works with the rest of the
codebase okay and at the end if you're
using the trunk based development what
you have is something potentially
releasable because it has everyone's
changes in it absolutely and one of the
important thing is to make sure that
trunk remains releasable so what we do
is anytime we are not releasable let's
say the game doesn't compile or some
assets are broken like there's a missing
dependency or something like that that
means we can't really release the game
what we do is we stop the line so to
speak and we lock the depot so nobody
can check in any more changes to the
trunk and what we do at that point is
trying to quickly as possible to
identify the change that caused this
problem once we identify that as opposed
to then trying to fix that because now
we are potentially blocking a lot of
people are trying to commit back to
trunk we identify the change and we back
out the change you basically remove the
change from the source control and the
developer responsible can come up with a
fix in their own time we found that it's
a lot less stressful because if the
developer trying to come up with the fix
once everybody is blocked it could be
very stressful for developers so by
backing out the change as quickly as
possible we go back to a releasable
state and let other people carry on do
you have a technique for quickly
identifying the offending change well
it's a lot of it is tribal knowledge but
one thing that definitely helps is
fewer changes we have in any given build
the easier it is to identify when we
looking at let's say I don't know two
three four changes it's easier to edit
for which one contributed the problem
then if you're looking at I don't know
50 or 100 or even potentially longer or
more changes there so but key trying to
keep the number of changes small it
helps to identify this that's the right
thing I would say it's the most
important part
okay so it's the number of changes that
are batched into a given build exactly
and again this is a part of continuous
integration there trying to work in
small batches by committing frequently
and validating small batches it
significantly helps because also it
reduces the risk because we have found
in the past when if there were a lot of
changes going in each change might work
fine individually but they might
interact badly with each other and
you're not gonna know that until you are
combining this with everything else so
if you are looking at like you try to
weather the hundred changes together
there's a chance that some of them might
just interact badly with each other and
you get that kind of failure I see and
another technique that allows us to work
to do trunk based development is using
feature toggles because one of the
challenges is if everybody's working on
the same branch and some features are
still in progress which means that we
don't necessarily want to release that
to players how to kind of hide these
features because traditionally using
feature branches is one way of solving
this problem because the code is not
even on the branch that you are very see
whereas what we found is by there are
two techniques one is branch by
abstraction so you could just have let's
say different if-else statement so we if
you use having different code path so we
can develop the other code path whilst
the other one is being used that's one
way which is then could be the feature
toggles so by choosing to switch off
certain code paths through feature
toggles we prevent playing seeing it and
we achieve that in two ways one is we
call it component
Tuggle beach at compile-time we strip
out any code that are behind those
features so we don't actually ship any
of that and players that's one way of
doing it which is good in one way but at
the same time it's not very flexible
once it's compound out if you need
another build with the featuring level
you have to basically make two builds
another approach is we use dynamic tacos
and that means the code is not stripped
out still is in the package and
executable but we can choose to toggle a
feature on or off ideally even for
different set of players based on
certain criteria and that's where we use
our services to help drive that because
we can change these little toggles and
the services can tell the client to to
load certain features or not
okay so feature toggles I understood I
understood that some of them can be
static and stripped out by the compiler
whereas others are dynamic and are
essentially flags that are evaluated at
runtime but you mentioned a term branch
by abstraction and then quite follow
what that was or how that was related
you kind of have your you have your
branches but back in code and like as I
said let's say you have an interface and
you have implemented that interface in
one way and now you want to come up with
a different interface let's say you have
an algorithm for I don't know let's say
your path finding you want to find a
path and it's implemented a certain way
and you think you know coming up with a
better way of doing it and let's say it
takes a while for you to kind of write
and finish that that new algorithm again
traditionally like somebody might just
work on the whole algorithm locally on
their PC once they're happy they check
it in and overwrite the old algorithm
that's one way of doing it which is not
great because you don't get really
feedback about your change once you are
working on this locally so a better
approach is to using the interview don't
even have an interface you can create an
interface in the first place as a first
step and put your implementation as in a
class that is implementing that
interface at the same time you can
create another implementation and
develop your algorithm in the other
class
implements this interface but nothing is
referencing this new interval so you can
easily check in your change and nobody
would be using it you could you might
choose to somehow toggle it on it could
be the comparative feature toggles or
just locally if you want to change the
implementation to use the new algorithm
and once you're happy you just switch
over and you can leave the old algorithm
there in case there's a problem and you
want to roll back to the other algorithm
and once you're happy you can just
completely remove the old algorithm I
use the new one okay I think I
understand now so you had some code that
instantiates a pathfinder and that codes
referring to the pathfinder interface
and maybe the implementation was an
a-star pathfinder and you want to
replace it with a something different
like an AI pathfinder or something yeah
and what you can do is just create a new
implementation and in one branch of code
either me perhaps using a feature toggle
you instantiate one or the other
exactly yes cool the next thing I wanted
to talk about was prototyping you you
mentioned some interesting things about
prototyping in our talk one thing you
said was that you had a methodology for
preventing prototyping code from getting
into production can you talk about that
absolutely yes so when we started with
this project because given like we were
learning how to work in a different way
we found that it's actually easier if we
start with a small core team who
understood this concept and like the
testing automated testing all the stuff
that we talked about here already so
they started and building the
foundations for the codebase but at the
same time we wanted to prototype a lot
of ideas just to prove them out and make
sure we can answer a lot of questions
and we really didn't want to mix these
two together again in the past what we
found is that particular code what end
up actually be your production code the
nobody really wants but they is hard for
them to go and justify
we implement that again because somebody
might say that how but I have seen this
feature now it looks good why don't we
just use that why do you want to go and
rewrite that with the high quality so
what we did was to kind of isolate this
core team so they can carry on working
on the codebase and at the production
quality well the same time allows us to
answer those questions
we formed a different team which was the
prototype team and they even used a
different engine for prototyping we use
unity engine and for the for the main
game we are using unreal for the people
who are interested and by actually
separating them there was no way for us
to actually bring the code back from
prototype into production so we could be
almost like fast and loose on prototype
codebase there obviously there was no
need to write a lot of tests you just
had to have some small number of tests
to make sure like for instance the game
doesn't crash and they could go really
fast kind of answer a lot of questions
and you can delete the code rewrite it
again however many times they needed and
once we answer those question we went
back to unreal and started to
implementing it from scratch ok was what
you're trying to prove in the
prototyping phase the viability of the
game or was it the continuous delivery
process no it was mainly the game itself
not the other process sometimes if
mainly we use the prototyping to answer
questions about the game stuff but
sometimes if you were going to evaluate
other nurse the different technology or
a different tool to use we would use
that we would prototype that as well but
that would be a separate branch
completely again it's a is a branch that
we create to answer this question and
throw it away it was never intended that
we work on a separate branch and then
bring that into our main that was there
mainly to see to base an experiment
because what we what we don't want to
happen is you spend a lot of time trying
to improve the quality of something that
you're not sure you're going to need
because if it turns out that feature
that you working on is no use there is
no point in let's say adding any test
for that because you're gonna throw that
away at the
of your experiment so it helps a lot
with experimentation but that was kind
of how we started at the beginning but
now we are prototyping more and more in
unreal itself but again I think because
now we kind of feel like we reach a
certain maturity level that our
developers understand the difference
between the part of our code the
production code and the dangers in
trying to kind of write protocol code we
didn't give that to and potentially
release that to I don't know four or
five million players there and causing
incidents and crashes in the game which
nobody wants to do so now that we are in
this kind of we are kind of more mature
and understand is better we are using
prototyping using unreal but again on a
different branch and the purpose is
again to just answer some questions and
then go back to the main branch and
implement a feature from scratch
that was actually packed with a lot of
information that that responds because
many of our listeners may not know about
game engines and maybe we could say
something about what a game engine is
for and how unity and unreal are
different sure yes
so gaming genes are in a way like
engines of engine of the game and a lot
of kind of they provide lot of libraries
and functionality similar to frameworks
if you think about it that let's say
there is a networking library there's a
physics library there is a rendering
library so you could use those to
develop your game as opposed to have to
go and implement almost low-level
functionalities from scratch and the
idea is that those are reusable part of
the game code that potentially other
games could use as well people try to
combine them all together and release
them as an engine I think as I said
probably the closest thing is like
frameworks that
other people develop let's say dotnet
framework is another example that you
can write down a code that uses that
framework itself to
chief your desired outcome and we have
like I said we use Unreal and unity
those are the two engines have used and
at the time we found that unreal suited
our needs better compared to unity for
what we were trying to achieve my
impression of Unreal was that it for C++
projects a lot of companies or teams
will choose unreal and unity had some
different options in terms of
programming languages you could use
c-sharp you could use like a JavaScript
like scripting language and it wasn't
necessarily as geared towards squeezing
the last bits of performance out but was
really good for prototyping yeah no
absolutely that's cool that's great
that's exactly right
although unreal has a concept of
blueprint which is kind of like
scripting but is visual scripting which
you can kind of have nodes and then
lines the basic each node achieve
something and then you connect them so
you can kind of create a flow of of
actions happening and the idea that they
have is by using this then you can in
theory prototype in unreal as well which
is what we use for prototyping but
that's you're quite right in terms of
the difference between the two a lot of
Triple A games still prefer unreal but
I'm sure unity is catching up and
improving a lot but it does seem to
provide a hard barrier where some code
written in unity is not really
compatible with with unreal and that's
how you're able to achieve that clean
separation correct yes absolutely yes
yeah great well I think we covered most
of what I wanted to talk about in the
implementation part and I wanted to talk
more about quality and testing
absolutely yes the next thing I wanted
to talk about is quality and testing
sure first how do you judge the quality
of a game that is it's an interesting
topic for us as well because I have to
mention before we actually release the
game in March for about a year and a
half
we were releasing the game to small
number of players which we call a we had
the program called technical alpha so a
lot of people could get the game and
play the game and the that was one of a
hot topic for us to discuss because we
were saying what is the accepted level
of quality especially like for instance
do we expect the same level of quality
when we are releasing the game to other
let's say 10,000 players versus whammies
release to 5 million players should they
have the same quality she would not have
the same level of quality but at the
same time we want something that when we
release is still visually looks good so
there's a lot of discussion happened but
still and like this is a topic that we
discussed especially given we are as I
mentioned we're trying to make sure we
have attained age release candid so this
topic keeps coming up and say this park
that we have is this really prevent us
from shipping the game or is that is
this actually okay we our players would
accept that and I think a lot of it is
also related to the expectation that
players have from your your title and
your game but what we generally say is
if something blocks people from
progressing in the game that is usually
a blocker and it's not accepted because
we don't want to be the case we want
people to see be able to play the game
maybe there is a workaround maybe there
is a park and there's a workaround that
we can communicate if we do that then we
can say actually we just communicate
this and then we fix it especially given
we already seen weekly we can release it
in the next release but if we find that
something like I don't know you trying
to sell an item in the game let's say
and it crashes and means out then
players cannot play the game anymore
that is a blocker and we don't release
visually again it depends on who you ask
I think like for instance artist
probably obviously they would like the
quality to be amazing but sometimes we
can afford to not hold back their
release to fix some visual glitches but
again it it completely depends it is I
think quite subjective
so we talked about manual testing and
the army of testers that you have and
how you're trying to reduce your
reliance on manual testing and focus
more on automated tests and you said
that I think 80 to 90 percent of the
tests were unit tests so let's talk a
little bit about the details of the
implementation
what are these tests like how are they
written and how are they run sure
so in unreal we could write two types of
tests we can write them in blueprint as
I mentioned with that kind of visual
diagram to say like you are launching a
client then you expect this thing to
happen and this is the you're asserting
that certain thing happened and you can
easily do that in blueprint visually and
that's how we started the benefit of
that is it's a lot easier to than write
tests but what we found is these tests
take a lot of time a long time to
actually run and they are very
complicated and you can easily create
these complicated blueprints that nobody
really understands how they work and you
can't really enforce any starting or
anything on them so we tend to move away
from that now and we try to write our
tests in C++ code in the engine itself
because unreal comes with an automation
framework itself but what when we
started it was lacking some sort of
functionalities that we needed at the
time so we ended up expanding that and
give more functionalities to that so we
are directly writing our tests in the
the game engine yeah so the blueprint
it's in some sense easier to write but
it can be hard to understand it's hard
to maintain because you can't
necessarily look at it and even
understand what it's trying to test yeah
that could be the case yes yeah and on
top of that it takes a long time to run
yes so now you're moving towards writing
more tests and C++
in the engine itself yes and you
mentioned that unreal has its own
automated testing framework but that
didn't quite meet your needs yes so we
kinda had to expand that yes we had to
switch to write most of our tests in C++
they were easier to maintain and they
were significantly faster to run
obviously the downside was he wasn't he
needed some basic training in order to
be able to write these new tests but
there were more reliable tests at the
same time one of the challenges we have
as I mentioned we have about 60,000
tests and we get some flaky tests and
these are the tests that are
non-deterministic s-- so which means
that you might run them once and they
might fail and with the same code you
run it again and they might pass the
second time so you're not really sure if
the problem is with the code or B the
test itself and what we found is
actually a lot of our tests they were
written in blueprint where these flaky
tests there so that was again another
reason to not write any new test in
blueprint and instead try to write them
in C++ the main problem with with flaky
tests is that developers don't lose
confidence because they just run it
again and it works even if it fails and
the next time they they might just even
ignore this they are probably not
related to what I've changed is the test
that is not deterministic so the number
one problem is that people lose
confidence in the pipeline or automation
system but also running the test again
takes time so you're adding time to to
your end-to-end time there so by
tackling this flaky test you not only
you improve the confidence but also
reduce the time it takes to run these
tests and what we found is actually
having fear tests that are deterministic
is much better than having loads and
loads of tests that are
non-deterministic sand you can't really
rely on them so what we what we do is
when we find a flaky test we try to
quarantine them and either
developer tries to fix the test in this
case if it's a blueprint
ideally they even try to try to deceive
most pass code but if it turns out that
the test isn't really providing value or
it's not really fit for purpose we go
and just delete that test because we
rather not to have that test as opposed
to having this test that gives us a lot
of noise but it is really important to
stay on top of these flaky tests okay so
it sounds like a test that is flaky
which means basically it's
non-deterministic sometimes when you run
it passes and sometimes it fails you
consider that to be just as good as
having no test at all pretty much so yes
yes okay which is a bit controversial
and now some people might disagree but
at the same time if if there's they fail
and then it kind of people lose trust
and even when they fail the people who
stop looking at them okay so it might
actually even have a worse be worse than
having no test yes yeah because what we
do is when as I said when we remove a
test because we think this test is
invaluable and if it turns out that we
were wrong and are there was a bug that
we missed we go on we can go at that
point we definitely know that there's a
value in this test so we can go and
write a test properly this time okay do
you have an example of one of these
flaky tests to illustrate the point
absolutely
so let's say test that kind of we had
tests that were fading or they might
pass depending on the order that they
got executed but those were because they
were not really isolated so it could be
a test that ran beforehand that changed
the state of the game or something and
then that this other test relied on
because Annie because it was not setting
it at the beginning correctly you're
just relying on on a state to be set to
a certain value that he might just fail
or pass depending on which other tests
ran beforehand so that was one cause for
us
the other one was sometimes especially
given like our game is client and server
so we had a test that kind of launches
the client then waits and launches the
server and then waits and then they
should connect with each other and how
we started again because because given
like we were learning how to write tests
we were kind of putting some random
waits to say let's say I launched the
client and launch the server and wait
for 10 seconds I would expect them to
connect and that might work fine to
begin with but as we add more content to
the game anyway I take longer to load so
you gradually takes longer to load and
then that 10 seconds might not be now so
when I get to about 9 seconds if you
happen to run on on an agent that is
slightly slower that might be just 11
seconds which means that you your search
would fade because it takes longer than
10 seconds and if I run another agent is
slightly faster and he might work also
relying on external dependencies like a
remote service if that service is down
your tests might fail and then he might
come back online and your test passes so
these are some examples like I think of
ok so the first example was some relying
on some precondition that you hadn't set
during the tests so I don't know maybe
some particular object being in some
particular place or exactly yes
something like that
the second one was something
timing-dependent yes that had to do with
loading assets or something of that
nature so relying on some precondition
that was timing dependent and the third
was a external service which may or may
not be available so how did you solve
those problems
so so the first one is obviously when
you find that this test wasn't setting
this state correctly is to make sure
like you you fix that I mean obviously
is hard to find because like because
calmly order dependent the other one is
like like we almost don't write any
tests anymore the wait for 13 seconds we
always try to change how we test this so
we don't have that and ideally even we
try to have as few tests as possible
that have to rely on a client to be
launched and a server being launched
then like all of these things because
that shows that that's not really a unit
test that's like kind of more like an
integration test so this question about
whether like like how many of those you
should have in the first place I mean
force us you need to have some that kind
of want to make sure that your client
and server connects but we tried again
not to
on time outs because said like as the
game size increases those those time
timeouts would eventually fail and the
other one about external dependencies
and services is either trying to mock
them so we don't have to really make
those calls if we can or alternatively
trying to run those services locally on
the same box that we running our client
and server so they don't have to do any
external communication let's say if the
connection to Internet drops for a few
seconds you don't want your test to fail
by running everything on the same
machine then you eliminate some of that
as well one thing we didn't talk about
yet was the actual deployment process
how the bits get on to the clients xbox
or pc could you talk about that
absolutely so the releasing a game for
any platforms it requires a
certification process by the platform
holder like Microsoft Sony Nintendo and
and even at releasing a mobile
application into iOS is fairly similar
in the sense that you have to go assert
certification process and the main
purpose of that is to ensure that the
quality of that platform meets the
expectation that the platform older
hands and the promises it gives to the
consumers of that platform that's why
they are there so there are they for
valid reasons but at the same time it
could be it could add significant amount
of time to the end-to-end time but for
us what we what we do is we when we make
our packages for clients for both Xbox
and PC we then have to upload that to
portal for the certification team to
verify the game is working as expected
and then once they prove then we can
release that to our players but given we
are releasing so frequently I think we
have done about 100 1890 releases so far
obviously requires significant amount of
resource from Xbox certification team to
verify
so what they had to do was they kind of
threw a lot of kind of great
conversation and collaboration with them
we came up with a different model that
helped out quite a lot we got to the
point where after the couple of
certification passes they kind of
trusted us to make sure the quality
meets their expectation so we could
release a lot faster
we submit through a certification
process but is we are kind of in a
almost like a bypass mode where they let
us go through the certification process
but what they do instead is they using
telemetry in production to monitor again
so for instance the crash rate they are
monitoring our crash rate and as long as
it remains under the certain level that
we agreed then everything is great we
can see a release yeah as fast and as
regularly as we are doing down but if
for some reason we are you know careful
and we make mistakes and the quality
drops then they can step in and try to
put more more pressure on us and put
more checks to make sure the title that
we are releasing meets their expectation
are their libraries or other code that
you have to bake into the binary so that
you get that telemetry data or is it
somehow automatically provided by the
platform yes they are provided by the
platform they are quite useful for us as
well because we can monitor now that the
game is released four five six months
roughly it really helps us as well
because we can see but when basically
the quality and stability of our title
using the same set of telemetry and
information there obviously we do a lot
of work and probably this is a topic on
itself we do a lot of work on telemetry
to post telemetry about the game about
how people play the game because what
one thing again contains the livery
allows us to do is experimentation so
and even do hypothesis driven
development so if somebody thinks they
we need to improve a metric we can work
on a feature release that and get some
telemetry to prove that was a good idea
or not
respond accordingly so we do a lot of
postal of telemetry ourselves but we at
the same time we use a lot from the
platform itself does that go back to
what you're talking about with the
feature flags or I think you call them
feature toggles so that you can sort of
start ratcheting up some of those
toggles to get to a subset of user or is
there another mechanism for how you test
that is the intention that's definitely
intention that we use the feature
toggles to release them to subset of
players at the moment when we release we
just release to everybody but we are
working on improving that but we are
using other mechanism to get some
feedback and release the game again
platform provides like these
capabilities for us having a different
set of players in it is called a
flighting program where you register
your users in different kind of these
different programs and then when you
release it only goes to these number of
players so we are using that as well but
that means again it's you basically to
solve me two packages to go to these
different audiences what we like to do
ideally is to still use the one package
and release it once but then different
set of players receive different sort of
features but that's for future work okay
that's for future work perhaps we can
have a follow-up absolutely well I think
we're up against time Jeff our so before
I wrap things up is there anything else
that we haven't covered that you'd like
to talk about no I think we covered
quite a lot again like the one thing
that changed for us since we launched is
now that we have to operate the game we
it comes with own challenges but again
that's probably a topic on its own but
other than that I think we covered quite
a lot great I I mentioned the talk that
you gave at the pipeline conference and
you told me offline that there was also
a version of that talk that you gave at
GDC so I'll include both of those in the
show notes that would the greatest thank
you okay
well Jeff result Ani is great having you
on software engineering radio for our
listeners thanks for listening and we'll
talk to you next time
thank you it was a pleasure being on
your podcast thank you great for
software engineering radio this has been
Nate black thanks for listening thanks
for listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SCO radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website that will reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio.com you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening